About

Which Greek Tragedies and Why

We are using four tragedies for our analysis:

Libation Bearers
Medea
Philoctetes
Women of Trachis

The first two plays, Libation Bearers and Medea, were selected because they depict women in pain. Philoctetes and Women of Trachis depict men in pain. This way, we have enough data to make conclusions about women's and men's pain.

Our Methodology

Creating the Corpus:

This project was originally derived from an adjacently related one, studying pain and gender in Greek tragedies. For that project, our group member, Vidya Surti, was awarded a UHC Research Fellowship to formulate her own 'Greek' tragedy adjacent play focusing on the gendered aspects of pain. During her preliminary research, she had already identified Greek tragedies that place a lot of focus on pain as a plot driver and an element that affects gendered perceptions of certain characters. We tried to divide the content of our corpus based on the type of pain being present. The tragedies we chose were Medea, Philoctetes, Women of Trachis, and Libation Bearers.

We had four group members, so we were each tasked with one tragedy to mark up.

Pain Markup (Trojan vs. Normal)

Our group did not opt to use the standard notation for our markup, with the pain instance wrapped in pain start and end tags. Ex.<pain>Pain Instance</pain> Instead, we opted to use Trojan markup, where we used an empty painStart element containing attributes and their values about the specific pain instance. After the painStart tag with the text of the pain instance, the painEnd tag would wrap the pain instance together. This painEnd tag would contain no attributes, unlike the painStart empty element. So, the painStart empty element would act as the start tag, and the painEnd empty element would act as the end tag. For each painEnd element, there must be a preceding painStart element. Furthermore, the document's markup must start with a painStart element and end with a painEnd element. There cannot be two painStart elements before a painEnd element, and the document cannot start with a painEnd element or end with a painStart element. So, we first marked up specific pain instances with the painStart and painEnd elements in each of our tragedies.

Here is an example of how we used Trojan Markup (the attributes will be introduced later in this methodology section):

<painStart painType="both" rec="Philoctetes" recGen="man" inf="disease" direct="no" recNorm="no"/>For my part, I pity him when I think how,with no one to care for him, and seeing no companion'sface, but suffering eternally alone, he is plagued by fierce disease and bewildered by each need as it arises.How, how does he endure his bitter fate?<painEnd/>

Determination of our attributes

During a meeting we had as a group, we determined and continued to refine the types of attributes that we thought would add specific layers of depth to our project. The attributes found in the painStart elements include information about the reciever and inflictor, the gender or non-human designation of people involved, the type of pain experienced, if the pain is direct or indirect.

Each painStart element required certain groupings of attributes.

Sources

Our Project

Our GitHub repository

Our Tragedies

Libation Bearers

Medea

Philoctetes

Women of Trachis

Analysis

How did the distribution of pain type differ by gender?

Looking at the numbers, there is a clear dichotomy of pain type by gender. The majority of women's pain experiences are of emotional pain, with instances of emotional pain comprising around 74% of all pain instances where a woman is receiving pain. On the other hand, the type of pain that men experienced was more evenly distributed between the three that we delineated, but they experienced physical pain most often, which is especially true given that our "both" category accounts for simultaneous experiences of physical and emotional pain.

What about experiences of direct and indirect pain?

When looking at women recieved pain and when men inflicted it, 44% of the pain was directly inflicted. Furthermore, with the same genders with indirect infliction, 55% of the pain was indirectly inflicted. Although the distribution was nearly equal, men tended to inflict pain indirectly more to woman than directly. On the other hand, with a woman inflictor, 55% inflicted pain directly, while 44% inflicted pain indirectly. So, women had a slight lean towards inflicting direct pain.

Who inflicted pain on who?

Interestingly enough, pain was usually inflicted upon the opposite gender, with women inflicting pain on men being the most common occurrence. There does not seem to be much of a trend for the mixed gender groups, although that is likely due to the fact that only a small proportion of pain instances involved them.

Conclusion

Experiences of Pain by Gender

As discussed on the analysis page, there were clear associations between female pain receivers and emotional pain, and male pain receivers and physical pain. This shows us that the pain in these four Greek tragedies is indeed gendered, and gendered in the way that one would expect.

We additionally marked up "direct" and "indirect" instances of pain, which was both a necessity and a way for us to add another layer to our analysis. We wondered if perhaps women would experience more indirect pain, since women are stereotypically thought to worry more about situations even when they have not directly been hurt. Our results did show a slight trend—women were slightly more likely to experience indirect pain than direct pain. On the other hand, male receivers of pain were almost evenly split between experiencing direct and indirect pain, but there were still 4 more instances of direct pain than indirect pain. This tells us that our hypothesis may have been correct, although we would need more data to draw a less tentative conclusion.

Dynamics Between Inflictors and Receivers of Pain

Our data shows that male receivers of pain were more likely to experience pain because of women, while female receivers of pain were more likely experience pain because of men. The former trend was particularly noticeable, and this is corroborated by the fact that the most common recRel attributes in our data were "husband" and "children," which correspond to the infRel attributes of "wife" and "mother."

One reason for the prominence of this trend is that out of the four Greek tragedies we analyzed, Medea and Women of Trachis had the largest numbers of pain instances, and both plays feature a woman as one of the main characters—Medea in Medea, and Deianeira in Women of Trachis. There are several instances when Medea hurts her children, and a large part of the Women of Trachis storyline is about the consequences of Deianeira inadvertently causing harm to her husband Heracles. This aligns with the fact that women have often been portrayed in familial contexts in fiction, rather than situations outside of family and home.

Our third most common recRel and infRel attribute values was "lover," which appeared together in 21 pain instances. 13 of these instances were men inflicting pain upon women, so we can see that the four Greek tragedies we analyzed, men also inflict pain to the people they are close to. However, the correlation is weaker, which reveals a dichotomy where male inflictors of pain are more likely to be in a wider variety of situations, while female inflictors of pain are more likely to appear in familial situations than others.

Gender, Pain Inflictors, and Norms

The most prominent trend in our data was the relationship between female inflictors of pain and Greek norms. There were 82 instances across the four tragedies where a female inflictor did not fit the norm, and only 2 instances where a female inflictor did fit the norm. In contrast, male inflictors of pain typically did fit Greek norms— there were 62 instances where a male inflictor fit the norm, and 12 instances where he did not. There were only 5 instances where the inflictor was a mixed gender group, and the split between fitting norms and not fitting norms was 2:3.

The fact that female inflictors of pain overwhelmingly did not fit Greek norms while male inflictors of pain typically did shows us that it is much less acceptable for women to inflict pain than it is for men.

However, we must note that the we didn't research ancient Greek culture extensively for this project to create a broad set of norms, so the data could be skewed due to a lack of standardization. For this project, we decided that who fit the norm and who didn't was more subjective based on the characters of the play. This subjectivity may be one reason for the big correlation between female inflictors and not fitting norms, as Deianeira was often marked as not fitting Greek norms for inadvertently hurting Heracles due to the active role she took, and the slight switch in gender roles between the two.

Limitations

We started our project a few weeks late because we had to switch topics, which meant that we lost some time that we could have had to refine our project and our project website. We did not standardize our infRel and recRel attributes, which is something that may have helped with collecting clearer data, and we did not check each other's markup for interpretive consistency across tragedies.

Furthermore, the conclusions we have drawn are limited by the fact that our corpus only consisted of four Greek tragedies. Extending our analysis to more Greek tragedies would allow us to be more certain about the patterns that we have observed and whether they hold true for Greek tragedies in general.

Final Thoughts

We concluded that a lo

Gendered Pain in Greek Tragedy

Research Questions and Theoretical Framework

Our research questions were central to our methods. Additionally, our research was guided by our understanding of patriarchy and sexism. We wanted to explore whether traditional tropes of sexism exhibited themselves through pain, specifically from the perspective of the original intended audience. By examining how pain is portrayed, inflicted, and experienced, we hope to understand how sexism operates in Greek tragedies. Our exploratory analysis and markup were guided by these research questions:

How do depictions of pain in Greek Tragedies differ between men and women?
Are depictions of experiencing and inflicting pain in greek tragedies distributed equally among men and women?

We are using a binary definition of gender, and we are looking at the greek tragedies we planned to analyze in a vacuum. In other words, we didn't look at these tragedies in context of the preceding plays.

Our Team

About the Developers

Alexis, an English Writing major with a minor in Film Studies, is a sophomore at the University of Pittsburgh. She joined this class, with no prior knowledge of coding, to fulfill a Quantitative Reasoning requirement in her degree. While learning the skill of resilience in the academic realm, this course in Computational Humanities has challenged Alexis in new ways. In regards to our research, Alexis was excited to combine gender studies and Greek poetry, two topics she has focused on in the past.

Cherina is a sophomore, double majoring in Biological Science and History and Philosophy of Science at the University of Pittsburgh. She joined this class to fulfill an honors credit, and because she is interested in the humanities. Because this course applies computational methods to the humanities she knew she would be able to apply the technical skills and knowledge gained in this course to future projects. Cherina found our research to be a great opportunity to analyze how pain relates to gender through one of her interests in humanities, which is literary analysis and interpretation.

Richa, a sophomore at the University of Pittsburgh, is a double major in Computational Biology and Anthropology, while also pursuing a certificate in Global Health. She joined this class because she saw it as a unique opportunity to bring together seemingly distinct disciplines. While she has a background in CS, she has learned many new technologies in this course. Pertaining to our research, Richa has a distinct interest in perception and the embodiment of pain.

Vidya is a sophmore at the University of Pittsburgh, double majoring in English and Anthropology. Vidya is also minoring in Chemistry. She joined this class to learn how to use different computer tools and languages to conduct research in the humanities. Vidya's favorite Greek tragedy is Medea, which was one of our main inspirations for our research topic.

Caroline, a TA who helped guide us through every aspect of our project,

Charlie, a TA who also helped guide us though our project, is a double major in Art History and Classics with a minor in French. Charlie plans to get her Ph.D. in Art History. She wanted to become a TA for this class because she loves working with students and seeing all of the impressive project each semester.